What‘s your favourite flavour?
你最喜欢的味道是什么？
Maybe you like your grub nice and spicy?
也许你喜欢食物又香又辣的味道？
Perhaps you have a sweet tooth?
也许你喜欢吃甜食？
Or are you partial to a salty, savoury snack?
或者你偏爱咸香的小吃？
By now you’re probably imagining something delicious, but take a moment to ponder this: why do some people adore certain flavours while others can‘t stand them?
此时你可能正在想象一些美味的东西，但花点时间思考一下这个问题：为什么有些人喜欢某些味道，而另一些人却无法忍受呢？
For example, oysters.
例如，牡蛎。
They turn my stomach, but some spend lavishly on the slippery shellfish.
它们让我反胃，但有些人却会大把花钱去买这种滑溜溜的贝类海鲜。
According to celebrity chef Heston Blumenthal, our taste preferences are strongly linked to our memories.
根据名厨赫斯顿·布卢门撒尔的说法，我们的口味偏好与我们的记忆紧密相连。
Certain flavours might bring back the sounds and smells of a seaside holiday, or an ice-cream might trigger memories of enjoying a childhood treat.
某些味道可能会让你回忆起在海边度假时的声音和气味，或者一个冰淇淋可能会引发对童年享受美食的回忆。
This “positive nostalgia” has a powerful effect on how we experience food.
这种“积极的怀旧情绪”对我们如何感受食物有着强大的影响。
Likewise, our surroundings have an impact on culinary pleasure.
同样，我们的周围环境对烹饪带来的愉悦感也有影响。
The same glass of wine can taste different depending on the background music.
同一杯葡萄酒，根据背景音乐的不同，品尝起来的味道也会不一样。
Blumenthal believes playing loud music makes people eat more quickly, while classical music makes them spend more money on wine.
布卢门撒尔认为，播放嘈杂的音乐让人吃得更快，而古典音乐则会让人们在葡萄酒上花更多的钱。
Alongside memory and ambience, our genetics also have a powerful impact on taste preferences.
除了记忆和氛围之外，我们的基因对口味偏好也有着巨大的影响。
Neuroscientist Charles Zucker from Columbia University believes all animals are “pre-wired” to prefer sweet tastes over sour.
哥伦比亚大学的神经学家查尔斯·祖克认为，所有动物生来就“预先设定”了喜欢甜味胜过酸味。
“There are no lions out in the wild drinking tonic water,” he says.
“在野外没有狮子会去喝通宁水。”他说。
On a more individual level, our personal genetic inherited preferences are significant.
在更个人的层面上，我们每个人继承下来的基因偏好是很重要的。
“And that is likely to greatly impact how much sugar I want to have in my coffee,” says Dr Zucker.
“而且这很可能会极大地影响我想在咖啡里放多少糖。”祖克博士说。
“It might be that I need six spoons of sugar to get the same level of satisfaction and reward that you get with only two.”
“可能我需要放六勺糖才能获得和你放两勺糖时相同程度的满足感和愉悦感。”
Coffee is also an interesting example of how our tastes change over time.
咖啡也是一个有趣的例子，说明我们的口味是如何随着时间而变化的。
Most children don‘t like the maltiness of beer or the bitterness of strong coffee.
大多数孩子不喜欢啤酒的麦芽味或浓咖啡的苦味。
But many adults enjoy the social reward - the relaxing effects of alcohol or the stimulation gained by coffee.
但许多成年人享受其中的社交回报——酒精带来的放松效果或咖啡带来的提神作用。
These are what we call acquired tastes - things we gradually learn to like - whether it’s because our palates become more sophisticated, or because we crave the social effects of the foods.
这些就是我们所说的后天养成的口味——我们逐渐学会去喜欢的东西——无论是因为我们的味觉变得更具鉴赏力，还是因为我们渴望食物带来的社交效应。
For me though, I‘m yet to see the allure in oysters, whether social or epicurean!
不过，对我来说，我还是没看出牡蛎的魅力，无论是从社交方面还是从美味方面来说！